Holliday Bookshop Collection, 1921-1979
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Holliday Bookshop Collection
1921-1979
Holliday Bookshop
9
1 box (0.5 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Husband and wife co-owners of a bookshop in New York City that initially specialized in importing English books, as well as offering unusual and rare books, especially first editions of contemporary authors and private press books. Contains book catalogues, correspondence, writings, publicity, and photographs.
Historical Note
Terence Holliday, an avid reader, worked at Brentano's in 1919, in order to learn "something about the book business." In 1920, Terence and his wife Elsa (Smith class of 1911) opened their bookshop on 10 West 47th Street in New York City. The bookshop began to slowly grow, despite the Holliday's choice to ignore the advice of Frank Crowningshield of Vanity Fair, to "have a couple of attractive young ladies serve tea in the shop every afternoon." Initially, the bookshop specialized in importing English books, as well as offering unusual and rare books, especially first editions of contemporary authors and private press books. Later, the Hollidays promoted the works of younger British and American poets and novelists, such as W. H. Auden, Thornton Wilder, Virginia Woolf, Aldous Huxley, Katherine Mansfield, William Faulkner, and T. S. Eliot.
In 1925, the bookshop moved to 49 West 49th Street. This location was a propitious one, since there were specialty bookshops in the area. Rather than competing for customers, the bookshops cooperated, making referrals and placing orders for each other. Unfortunately, some of the larger publishers in competition with the Holliday were not nearly as gracious. The import of English editions was made difficult by the existing copyright laws, and the invention of "limited editions" from the larger houses also threatened business.
The Hollidays weathered the Depression, with Terence lecturing occasionally and writing articles to make ends meet. However, by 1950, the difficulties of running the bookshop began to wear on Terence, and the Hollidays began to look for a buyer for their shop. A run of bad luck ensued, including two destructive fires of suspicious origin.
In 1951, the Hollidays sold their bookstore to Robert T. Vanderbilt, and retired in Milford, Connecticut. Terence Holliday died in 1969 at the age of 84. Elsa Detmold Holliday died in 1991 at the age of 100. After 31 years of existence, the Holliday bookshop had become more than a bookshop; it had become an "Institution."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The archive of the Holliday Bookshop contains book catalogues, correspondence, writings, publicity, and photographs, dating from 1921 to 1979. The archive was donated to the Mortimer Rare Book Room in 1994 by John Detmold, in memory of his aunt, Elsa Detmold Holliday, class of 1911. The collection is divided up into five series, in 52 folders.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Book Catalogues, 1921-1937
II. Correspondence, 1921-1973
III. Publicity, 1924-1979
IV. Writings, 1929-1930
V. Photographs
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided up into five series, in 52 folders.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Holliday Bookshop Collection is the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of the works or their legal representatives.
History of the Collection
The archive was donated to the Mortimer Rare Book Room in 1994 by John Detmold, in memory of his aunt, Elsa Detmold Holliday, class of 1911.
Search Terms
Holliday, Terrance.; Holliday, Elsa Detmold.; Holliday Bookshop.; Bookstores--New York (State)--New York.; Holliday, Terrance.; Holliday, Elsa Detmold.
- Series I. Book Catalogues, 1921-1937
  Series I. consists of book catalogues written and distributed monthly by the Hollidays (folders 1-8). These catalogues were the source of the majority of their business, as well as being valuable references for collectors and librarians.
- Series II. Correspondence, 1921-1973
  Series II. contains the Bookshop correspondence, including cards and letters from Archibald MacLeish, Louisa Brooke Jones, and Mrs. Theodore Roosevelt (folders 8-34).
- Series III. Publicity, 1924-1979
  Series III. consists of publicity surrounding the bookshop, including an advertisement which ran in the first issue of the New Yorker, information on the sale of the shop, and various reviews and articles written about the bookshop (folders 35-45).
- Series IV. Writings, 1929-1930
  Series IV. consists of writings by Elsa and Terence Holliday, including a history of the bookshop, and an article on bookselling for Encyclopedia Britannica (folders 46-49).
- Series V. Photographs
  Series V. contains photographs of the Hollidays, and their close friends Irving and Ellen Berlin (folders 50-52).
- Series I. Book Catalogues, 1921-1937
  - Books to Read and Re-read 1921, [1 item] (Folder 1)
  - Catalog of Modern and Contemporary Books n.d., [1 item] (Folder 2)
  - Holliday Books for Christmas 1930-1950, [20 items] (Folder 3)
  - The Holliday Book Shop. Current Books, No. 8-10 1924, [3 items] (Folder 4)
  - The Holliday Book Shop. New & Forthcoming Books, No. 11-20 1925-1929, [9 items] (Folder 5)
  - The Holliday Book Shop. New & Forthcoming Books, No. 21-23 1929-1931, [3 items]. (Folder 6)
    No. 23 annotated in pencil on the back cover.
  - 100 Good Books [1937], [1 item] (Folder 7)
  - Ten Favorite Books n.d., [1 item] (Folder 8)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1921-1973
  - Bogan, Louise. ALS 1943 Aug 1 (Folder 9)
  - Brandt & Brandt. TLS 1952 Mar 18 (Folder 10)
  - Brandt & Brandt. TLS 1952 Mar 31 (Folder 10)
  - From Elsa Holliday. TL 1952 Apr 1 (Folder 10)
  - Brandt & Brandt. TLS 1952 Apr 3 (Folder 10)
  - From Elsa Holliday. TL 1952 May 14 (Folder 10)
  - Brandt & Brandt. TLS 1952 May 20 (Folder 10)
  - Carter, John and Ernestine. Card and envelope 1940 Dec 27 (Folder 11)
  - Curtiss, Mina. TLS 1951 Aug 4 (Folder 12)
  - Doubleday, Page and Co. TLS 1924 Feb 24 (Folder 13)
  - From Holliday Book Shop. TL 1924 Feb 25 (Folder 13)
  - Doubleday, Page and Co. TLS 1924 Feb 27 (Folder 13)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica. TLS 1928 Sep 14 (Folder 14)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica. TLS 1928 Sep 20 (Folder 14)
  - From Terence Holliday. TLS 1928 Sep 27 (Folder 14)
  - Fletcher, Frank Irving. TLS 1923 Jul 20 (Folder 15)
  - Gregg, Eleanor and Alan. ALS 1951 Oct 22 (Folder 16)
  - Harpers' Bazaar. TLS 1938 Jul 19 (Folder 17)
  - Holliday, Terence and Elsa. ACS 1921, 2 copies (Folder 18)
  - Holliday Book Shop. TL 1924 Dec 4 (Folder 19)
  - Jones, Louisa Brooke. ACS 1943 Aug 12 (Folder 20)
  - Jones, Louisa Brooke. ALS 1951 Jul 26 (Folder 20)
  - MacLeish, Archibald. TLS 1943 Aug 9 (Folder 21)
  - Marshall, Lenore G. ALS 1943 Aug 10 (Folder 22)
  - McFee, William. ALS and envelope 1922 Nov 27 (Folder 23)
  - New Yorker
    - Advertising Dept. TLS 1925 Mar 16 (Folder 24)
    - Advertising Dept. TLS 1925 Mar 16 (Folder 24)
    - Editorial Offices. TLS 1975 Mar 11, 3 copies (Folder 24)
  - Peirce, Albert E. Care of Mrs. C. M. Thomas. 2 bills and ACS sent from Terence Holliday 1930 Jun 6 (Folder 25)
  - Random House. ACS 1938 Jun 29 (Folder 26)
  - Roosevelt, Mrs. Theodore. ACS n.y. Aug 31 (Folder 27)
  - Shawn, William. Draft letter by Elsa Holliday n.d. (Folder 28)
  - Simon and Schuster. TLS 1942 Apr 29 (Folder 29)
  - Simon and Schuster. TLS 1942 May 8 (Folder 29)
  - Simon and Schuster. TLS 1942 Jul 7 (Folder 29)
  - Smith College Library. TLS 1962 Jul 31 (Folder 30)
  - Smith College Museum of Art. TLS 1973 May 30 (Folder 31)
  - Sze, Marimai. ALS 1943 Aug 8 (Folder 32)
  - Sze, Marimai. ALS 1952 Jun 2 (Folder 32)
  - Whistler, Laurence. ALS 1952 Sep 19 (Folder 33)
  - Wilson, Edmund. ALS and transcript. 1951 Jul 29 (Folder 33a)
  - Unidentified [first initial V] n.d. (Folder 34)
- Series III. Publicity, 1924-1979
  - Advertisement for special edition of book entitled The Squire's Home-made Wines 1924 Feb. (Folder 35)
  - Article describing popularity of recent books from England at the Holliday Bookshop n.d. (Folder 36)
  - Article describing lecture given by Mrs. Terence Holliday at the American Association of University Women n.d. (Folder 37)
  - Bulletin of The New York Library Club. Includes speech made by Terence Holliday, "Not Everyone Reads Best Sellers" at the January Meeting 1930 Jan 30 (Folder 38)
    SEE ALSO: "Writings" for typescript version of speech, found loose inside bulletin which differs from version in bulletin.
  - Cartoon of the Holliday Book Shop. Caption reads "The Holiday Book Shop at 49 East 49th Street," n.d. (Folder 39)
  - "Holliday Bookshop sold to British Book Centre." Article from Publisher's Weekly in the "Retailing" section 1961 Apr 3 (Folder 40)
  - "A Magazine in Transition is the Talk of the Town." Article from New York Times on William Shawn and the New Yorker 1979 May 27 (Folder 41)
  - New Yorker. Reproduction of first issue, with advertisement for Holliday Book Shop on pg. 26 1925 Feb 21 (Folder 42)
  - Review of The Squire's Home-made Wines 1924 Feb (Folder 43)
  - Tallis, Thomas. Printed copy of inscription on tomb n.d. (Folder 44)
  - "Terence Holliday to Address Literary Department." Article from The Villager 1931 Dec 1 (Folder 45)
- Series IV. Writings, 1929-1930
  - HOLLIDAY, ELSA
    - "Holiday [sic] in Name Only." Mimeographed manuscript, annotated in pen. n.d., 39 pages (Folder 46)
    - "Holiday [sic] in Name Only." Typescript manuscript, annotated in pencil. n.d., 39 pages (Folder 46)
      Both copies are ascribed to both Elsa and Terence, but were written solely by Elsa.
      SEE ALSO: "Correspondence," Brandt and Brandt, regarding publication of the manuscript.
    - "The Literary Scene in New York in the 20's, 30's & 40's." Typescript draft of talk given by Elsa Holliday at meeting of American Association of University Women n.d. (Folder 47)
  - HOLLIDAY, TERENCE
    - "Bookselling in the United States." Typescript draft. For inclusion in the Encyclopedia Brittanica 1930 (Folder 48)
    - ["Not Everyone Reads Best Sellers"]. Typescript version of talk given at The New York Library Club. 1930 Jan 30 (Folder 49)
    - "Not Everyone Reads Best Sellers." Publishers's Weekly 1929 Jul 27 (Folder 49)
    - "Not Everyone Reads Best Sellers." Reprinted by The Holliday Book Shop from Publishers' Weekly.
- Series V. Photographs
  - 3 black and white photographs of Terence and Elsa Holliday. (Folder 50)
  - Ellen and Irving Berlin and 3 daughters. Photograph mounted on Christmas card. (Folder 51)
  - 3 color transparencies and one color photograph depicting Terence Holliday and a model at The Holliday Book Shop. (Folder 52)